We are up to מנחות Menachot and today is the last דף
daf for a while that is going to be talking about the
topic of מנחות, Menachot, then we will digress and turn to a
whole fascinating range of different topics, many of them quite relevant. But
for today, we are still on מנחות Menachot and we pick up
on our משנה. Mishna.
So משנה Mishna says the following: נטמאו שיריה, Nitme'u shi'areiha, if some
of the remnant of the, or the remnant, the שיריים shirayim after
one takes the קומץ kometz became טמא, tamei, נשרפו שיריה Nisrefu shi'areiha
or if it was burned, אבדו שיריה Avdu shi'areiha or it was
lost, so what do you do? Are you allowed to bring the
קומץ kometz if there is nothing left over? So it says: כמידת
רבי אליעזר כשרה, K'midat Rabbi Eliezer K'shira, according to רבי אליעזר's Rabbi
Eliezer position, in the phrase of the word כמידת, k'midat, we would
say like כשיטת רבי אליעזר, k'shitat Rabbi Eliezer, but you know this
is Mishnaic Hebrew, it would be כשרה. k'shira. וכמידת רבי יהושע פסולה,
U'k'midat Rabbi Yehoshua Psula, according to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua it is
invalid. We have not quoted the רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבי יהושע,
Rabbi Yehoshua, but elsewhere in ש"ס, Shas, because obviously you're coming with
the larger ש"ס Shas context, you are aware that there is a
debate that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua whether
you can be זורק את הדם zorek et hadam of a קרבן
korban if you have nothing left of it other than the blood
that is valid. Do you need there to be some fat to
burn on the מזבח mizbe'ach or some of the limbs, some meat
if it's an עולה olah to burn, or some meat to eat
if it's not an עולה? olah? So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
even if all you have is the blood, you can be זורק
את הדם zorek et hadam so that the קרבן korban can be
valid. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says no, you need there to
be something else that the דם dam is being a מתיר matir
for. So here too the same is true about the קומץ kometz
whether you need there to be שיריים shirayim or not. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב, Amar Rav,
so רב Rav says, והוא שנטמאו כל שיריה. v'hu shenitme'u kol shi'areiha.
When the משנה Mishna says they became טמא, tamei, it's going to
be a problem according to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, that's when all
of the שיריים shirayim became טמא. tamei. אבל מקצת שיריה לא, Aval
miktzat shi'areiha lo, but not only a minority, a smaller amount. Okay,
so basically what he's saying is is that there needs to be
something left. It doesn't have to be the whole thing. So even
if there is a little bit left,
maybe כזית kezayit worth and so on, but nevertheless even a little
bit, you do not need all of the remnant left. The גמרא,
Gemara, however, focuses on the fact that he uses the word נטמא.
nitma. And as we've just seen from the previous משנה Mishna and
the previous discussion, maybe טומאה tum'ah has some special status that allows
the problem to be obviated. So let's take a look at what
the גמרא Gemara says about this.
Sorry here Joey, get in over here. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this: מאי קסבר? Mai kasavar?
I'm sorry. קא סלקא דעתך Ka salka daitach we thought, said the
גמרא, Gemara, נטמא אין אבדו ושרוף לא. nitma in, avdu v'saruf lo.
When רב Rav says that if some of it remains and the
majority is נטמא nitma you're okay, that was a special הלכה halacha
by נטמא nitma because as we've seen, נטמא nitma has some leniencies
because of the idea of ציץ. tzitz. So now we want to
understand what would be this logic to say that נטמא nitma we'd
be more lenient but you would still only be talking about part
of it became טמא. tamei. So let's take a look.
Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי קסבר? Mai kasavar? What are
you of the opinion of? אי קסבר Ei kasavar if he's of
the opinion שיריים לאו מילתא היא shirayim lav milta hi that
a little bit, a little remnant is not sufficient and you need
all of it to be left over, ונטמא מאי טעמא? v'nitma mai
ta'ama? So why is נטמא nitma not a problem according to רבי
יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? דמרצה ציץ d'mratzeh tzitz because the ציץ tzitz sort
of makes it desirable, it
makes it acceptable, right? And that was the debate if you remember
yesterday about whether the ציץ tzitz works על האוכלין. al ha'ochlin. When
the גמרא Gemara yesterday says whether the ציץ tzitz works על האוכלין,
al ha'ochlin, it doesn't mean that because of the ציץ tzitz you
would be allowed to eat the meat. You know, ציץ tzitz only
works to make a קרבן korban valid, not to allow you to
eat something בטומאה. betum'ah. So what does it mean that the ציץ
tzitz works על האוכלין? al ha'ochlin? It means that as far as
making the קרבן korban valid is concerned, will the ציץ tzitz also
address problems that come up for the part of the קרבן korban
that's eaten? Meaning, you know, vis-a-vis if that will help the קרבן
korban be valid, will the ציץ tzitz let us bracket the problem
that the edible parts of the
קרבן korban are טמא? tamei? Now the easiest way you can see
that application is according to רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. Since רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua says for a קרבן korban to be valid there has
to be something left over, so let's say the only thing left
over is טמא. tamei. So if you say that the ציץ tzitz
is מרצה על האוכלין. mratzeh al ha'ochlin. אוכלים ochlin then according to
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua you could go ahead and still bring the
קרבן korban because even though there's nothing left over, the ציץ tzitz
makes it as if it's still כשר. kosher. So that's what the
גמרא's Gemara asking now here according to רבא. Rava. אי סבר שיורא
מילתא היא I savar shiura milta hi if he I'm sorry, let's
read it again. מאי קסבר mai kasavar what does רבא Rava hold?
אי סבר שיורא מילתא היא I savar shiura milta hi
if he says that a little bit that's left over is valid,
then אפילו אבד וששרף נמי afilu avad vesaraf nami why does he
single out טומאה? tumah? Even if most of it was lost or
burnt, if there's a little left over it should be good enough.
אי סבר שיורא לאו מילתא היא I savar shiura lav milta hi
if he thinks that the little bit left over is not significant,
you need all of it to be around, then נטמא מאי טעמא
nitma mai ta'ama so why is he saying that if it's נטמא
nitma רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would agree? דמרצה ציץ demiratzeh tzitz because
he says the ציץ tzitz makes it as if the טומאה tumah
was not around. Meaning the ציץ tzitz sort of papers over the
טומאה, tumah, not to the point that you could eat the שיריים
shirayim but to the point that the קרבן korban would be valid.
If that's true, so he's saying a special הלכה halacha about טומאה,
tumah, so יהא הכי כל שיורא נמי yehei hachi kol shiura nami
so it should not require that there be
a little left over. He should say his הלכה halacha even if
all of it became טמא tamei that the ציץ tzitz should work.
So the גמרא Gemara says you know what you're right. לעולם קסבר
שיורא מילתא
היא. le'olam kasavar shiura milta hi. Really רבא's Rava point was just
that you don't need all leftover, even a little leftover is enough.
ונטמא והוא הדין אבד וששרף, venitma vehu hadin avad vesaraf, don't get
hung up over the fact that רבא Rava said נטמא. nitma. When
he said נטמא nitma he didn't specifically mean נטמא, nitma, although I
understand your reason for thinking that נטמא nitma was special because of
the ציץ, tzitz, but that's not what he meant. He meant whatever
happened to it, whether it was טמא tamei or lost or burnt,
as long as a little bit is left over רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua would agree. והא דקאמר נטמא veha dekamar nitma so why did
he say if most of it was נטמא? nitma? Not because נטמא
nitma is special but רישא הוא נקט reisha hu nakat like the
beginning of the משנה, Mishnah, right? The משנה Mishnah starts with נטמאו
שיריה. nitme'u shireiha. Okay so now what have we said? We've said
a very simple point that when רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says you
need something left over in order to do the מתיר, mattir, whether
the מתיר mattir is the זריקת הדם zerikat hadam or the burning
of the קומץ, kometz, that he says that he does not require
all of the remnant to be present. It's enough that some of
what's left over is present. So if it's a קרבן korban it's
some meat, there's some חלב chelev or if it's a מנחה mincha
that there is some of the שיריים. shirayim. That suffices. But we
also said in parenthesis, which ties into yesterday, is that it's possible
that נטמא nitma would not be a problem even according to רבי
יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. That's not what the משנה Mishnah says, but in
theory that's possible because if the ציץ tzitz works על האוכלים, al
ha'ochlin, not only on things you put on the מזבח mizbe'ach but
even things that are to be eaten, so then it would be
considered like there is stuff left over even though you really can't
eat it because it's טמא tamei but the idea of the ריצוי
ציץ ritzui tzitz should allow us to bracket that.
Where did the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol go where?
Where did the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol what?
When he wore the ציץ?
tzitz? So that's a debate in the גמרא Gemara which is fascinatingly
we have yet to see it in the good whatever 130 דפים
dappim of קדשים Kodshim we've done so far, but the גמרא Gemara
discusses whether when we say the ציץ tzitz is מרצה, meratzeh, is
it only when the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is wearing the ציץ
tzitz or as long as the ציץ tzitz just is present? Meaning
unless it's broken or lost, but as long as the ציץ tzitz
is present even if it's not being worn. That's a debate in
the גמרא. Gemara.
You had it...
What? We did have it...
No, we talked about it...
We talked about it...
No, wasn't it... Was it in another גמרא? Gemara?
I don't
think we've actually seen that in the גמרא.
Gemara. We haven't. What? Did he wear it every day? Yeah, whenever
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
was there and did the עבודה, avodah, he that was part of
his normal בגדים, begadim, that was part of his normal you know
the normal outfit that he wore.
Oh so it means whatever was
טומאה tumah or something it doesn't make it...
It doesn't mean that לכתחילה l'chatchilah you would, but it means בדיעבד
bedi'avad if it was done that the קרבן korban is accepted.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying it would be כשר kosher even
if the whole שיריים shirayim were gone.
Yeah, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't need...
We haven't changed him.
No, this is all to limit רבי יהושע's...
Rabbi Yehoshua No I understand but it was going to suggest that
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, the גמרא's Gemara not debating so much and
you know...
No. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this, כדתניא kedatanya like
we taught in the ברייתא baraita that for רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
if a little is left over he would also agree that it's
okay. כדתניא kedatanya we taught in the ברייתא baraita רבי יהושע אומר
כל הזבחים שבתורה שנשתייר מהן כזית בשר או כזית חלב. Rabbi Yehoshua
omer kol hazvachim shebatorah shenishtayer mehen kezayit basar o kezayit chelev. So
you see it doesn't need all to be left over. All of
the animal sacrifices that as long as there's one כזית kezayit worth
of meat or one כזית kezayit worth of fat left over, even
if most of it was lost, זורק את הדם zorek et hadam
you can do the זריקת הדם. zerikat hadam. כחצי זית בשר כחצי
זית חלב kechatzi zayit basar kechatzi zayit chelev if it's only a
half a כזית kezayit of meat and a half a כזית kezayit
of fat, אינו זורק את הדם eino zorek et hadam you can't
do זריקה. zerika. ובעולה uva'olah but if you're talking about an עולה
olah קרבן, korban, אפילו כחצי זית בשר כחצי זית חלב זורק את
הדם afilu kechatzi zayit basar kechatzi zayit chelev zorek et hadam even
if it's only half a כזית kezayit of meat and half a
כזית kezayit of the fat you can do זריקת הדם. zerikat hadam.
Why? Because by an עולה olah you not only burn the fat,
you also burn the meat. So if you have a half of
a כזית kezayit of each,
it means you have a whole כזית kezayit of something you are
going to burn on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. But if it is not
an עולה, olah, the fact that you have a half a כזית
kezayit that you can eat and a half of a כזית kezayit
that you can burn does not mean there's a significant amount that
you can do any
one. but
you need a כזית kezayis of one or the other so that
it's said so that you can do זריקת הדם. zerikas hadam. So
you see there he does not need all to be left over,
and the same way he does not need all to be left
over by the animal קרבן, korban, he does not need all to
be left over by the מנחה. mincha. Okay. וב uba- so now,
מפני mipnei and here's why by the עולה olah it can be
combined, מפני שכולו כליל mipnei shekulo kalil because it's all burnt. So
half a כזית kezayis of meat and half a כזית kezayis of
fat is in the end of the day a כזית kezayis of
something that is burned. ובמנחה uvemincha by a מנחה mincha אפילו כולו
קיים afilu kulo kayam even if the whole מנחה mincha is around
לא יזרוק lo yizrok don't sprinkle the blood. So גמרא Gemara says
what does that mean first of all if it's all around what's
the problem? Second of all what type of sprinkling of the blood
happens by a מנחה? mincha?
גמרא Gemara says how much מנחה mincha left of the שיריים shiyayim
does he need have we talked about that?
Well we haven't talked about that. מנחה מאי עבידתא mincha mah avidteh
what is the relevance of a מנחה mincha here to sprinkling the
blood? אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa we are in כ"ו עמוד
א chaf vav amud aleph five lines down in the wide lines
middle of the line. אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa so says
רב פפא Rav Papa מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim we're not talking we're
still talking about an animal sacrifice and we're talking about the מנחה
mincha that comes with the wine that comes with the animal sacrifice.
So none of the meat of the animal is left but the
entire מנחה mincha that came with the animal sacrifice is left. Can
you do a זריקת הדם zerikas hadam because at least something that
is eaten is left although none of the meat? סלקא דעתך salka
daatach I would have thought הואיל ובהדי זבח קא אתיא ho-el uvahadei
zevach ka-atya since it's coming with the animal with the animal sacrifice
כגופיה דזבח דמי kegufeh dizevach dami
it's like the actual body of the sacrifice itself and it's like
something still remains and you can be זורק הדם zorek hadam קמשמע
לן kamashmalan that you cannot. Okay so here you see that רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says as long as a little bit is left
over it's enough, he needs there to be something left over כזית
kezayis
and the מנחה mincha that comes with the animal sacrifice is not
considered as part of the sacrifice itself. Now Michael asked the correct
question which is how much needs to be left over when you're
bringing a מנחה mincha if you want to bring the קומץ kometz
which is exactly the issue of our משנה. mishna. גמרא Gemara does
not say it says something מקצת miktzas but we said elsewhere that
the answer is also a כזית, kezayis, that the definition of what
is considered a הקטרה haktara a minimum amount that you would burn
is a כזית kezayis and actually to some degree you already see
that by an animal sacrifice because it's either a כזית kezayis of
the meat that you're going to eat or כזית kezayis of the
fat that you're going to burn. There also the concept of burning
הקטרה haktara the amount is a כזית. kezayis. Okay so let's take
a look. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this what
do you in if the whole thing then you just what do
you do with the- if you have the rest of the מנחת
נסכים minchas nesachim you would just burn it?
Yeah you'd have to burn it like it's פסול. pasul. Right okay
so now the whole קרבן korban is פסול pasul you're not going
to be זורק הדם. zorek hadam. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says
like this מנא
הני מילי minani mili where do we get this from? אמר רבי
יוחנן משום רבי ישמעאל Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yishmael so רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says in the name of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
which is pretty interesting right going straight back to a תנא tanna
although רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was like first generation. ומצא בה משום
רבי יהושע בן חנניה umotsavah mishum Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya and some
are inclined to say that this just comes from רבי יהושע בן
חנניה. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya. אמר קרא Amar kra the פסוק pasuk
says והקטיר החלב לריח ניחוח להשם. vehiktir hachelev lereach nichoach l'hashem. So
the פסוק pasuk says that you shall burn the fat. So רש"י
Rashi quotes the whole פסוק. pasuk. The whole פסוק pasuk is וזרק
הכהן את הדם על מזבח השם לפני אהל מועד ve-zarak hakohein es
hadam al mizbe'ach hashem lifnei ohel moed the כהן kohein will sprinkle
the blood and then it says והקטיר החלב vehiktir hachelev and then
you burn the fat לריח ניחוח להשם. lereach nichoach l'hashem. So it's
so as long as you are burning the fat that is enough
to sprinkle the blood. חלב אף על פי שאין בשר chelev af
al pi she-ein basar even if all you have is the fat
that's enough you don't need all of the remnant there. And once
you're saying we're learning from there that it's enough to have the
fat left to do the זריקת הדם zerikas hadam we say you
don't even need all the fat or you don't even need all
the meat you just need something of significance left over. So this
again is the debate of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you can do זריקת
הדם zerikas hadam and that's it that is you know the basic
קרבן korban is putting the blood on the מזבח mizbeach and if
you do that it's a good קרבן korban whereas רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua says no in order to do זריקת הדם zerikas hadam there
has to be something else one of the ways the blood functions
is as a מתיר matir it lets you move on to the
next stage burning fat eating meat and if it's not having that
function it's not good. So you need there to be you don't
need everything left over but you need there to be enough left
over that you can do something of significance with it. Okay so
now the
גמרא Gemara continues ואשכחן חלב ve-ashkechan chelev we found that it's enough
to be זורק הדם zorek hadam from the fat. יותרת ושתי כליות
מנלן yoseret u-shtei klayos minnalan now the to- we always just call
them like the entrails but it's not all fat right some of
it is actually organs there's actually the lobe of the liver which
is what's the lobe of the liver doctor?
Does the liver have some type of a little appendage there that's
like a bladder one of those what do you call those? No
is it liver or kidney?
No no
it's called the lobe of liver that's what it's called.
Oh okay.
Is that attached to the liver?
I don't think so.
We're not medical doctors.
You went to medical school once, right? No, no, not yet. Ah.
It's easy to get confused.
Okay,
anyway,
they're in the same area.
They're in the neighborhood.
They were cutting up all those animals, they must have seen the
liver.
Right, right, right.
Well, no, it's in the Torah. I mean, do we have a
Living Torah?
That's my daughter. What's the question?
What's the question? About the pancreas and the liver, are they connected?
Let's not get bogged down on this too much.
What?
I'm not sure they're physically
connected, but they're very close.
Pancreas and the liver.
There's a picture of pancreas and liver somewhere?
Yeah, I think it does. Okay, here. The lobe over the liver.
You know, if they only had, if he had only put his
stuff out, this Aryeh Kaplan Living Torah with a חומש Chumash with
רש״י, Rashi, you know, this would have been the standard English translation
and we would have been such a more of an educated people.
He has actually all of the, you know, historical and medical stuff,
pictures, whatever.
This is medical questions from the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay.
The lobe of the liver, usually identified as the caudate lobe, which
in ruminants rests on the right
kidney, and is connected to the pancreas or very close to the
pancreas.
Some say it's the diaphragm.
They are connected?
Connected. Now are they connected or just next to?
I don't know. I don't
remember anymore.
All right, anyway, anyway, it's the lobe of the liver.
Another model would be the way the adrenal is connected to the
kidney.
This shows you the stomach of the cow, this doesn't show the
lobe of the liver. Anyway, it's either the diaphragm or some lobe
attached to the liver and ושתי הכליות ushtei haklayot and the kidneys.
So this is also what was offered up together with the חלב.
chelev. So the question is, is it enough that these are left
over if none of the חלב chelev is left? Now, in our
mind, we have never distinguished between them. You know, there's a whole
bunch of stuff you put on the fire. Why should you distinguish
between whether it's fat or whether it's the lobe of the liver
and the kidneys? But, you know, the גמרא Gemara is saying, the
Torah says חלב, chelev, maybe the other stuff doesn't count as much.
So let's take a look.
Can they eat the liver or the kidney of a קרבן?
korban? Yeah, you could. No, I mean, no, what are you talking
about? You only do the lobe of the liver and the kidneys.
The rest of the internal organs you can eat. So it's the
כהנים kohanim if it's a קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim or the owners
if it's קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: ואשכחן חלב, ve'ashkechan chelev, so we found the fat. יותרת
ושתי הכליות מנלן, yoteret ushtei haklayot menalan, how do I know about
the lobe and the two kidneys that that's enough to burn in
order to do זריקת הדם? zrikat hadam? So the גמרא Gemara says:
דתני, detani, ובמנחה אפילו כולה קיימת לא יזרוק. uvmincha afilu kullah kayemet
lo yizrok. So this is not how we know it from the
פסוק, pasuk, but how we know it from that this is the
position of רבי יהושוע, Rebbi Yehoshua, because רבי יהושוע Rebbi Yehoshua says
that if all you have left is the מנחה, mincha, then you
cannot be, you cannot sprinkle the blood. מנחה הוא דלא יזרוק, mincha
hu delo yizrok, because all you have left is the מנחה, mincha,
don't sprinkle the blood. יותרת ושתי הכליות, yoteret ushtei haklayot, but if
what you have left is some of the actual meat of the
קרבן korban itself to burn on the מזבח, mizbeach, like the lobe
and the two kidneys, יזרוק, yizrok, you can do the sprinkling. So
at least we know that is the position of רבי יהושוע. Rebbi
Yehoshua. Okay, so רבי יהושוע Rebbi Yehoshua says as long as anything
is left of the actual animal itself, either a כזית kezayit worth
to burn, whether it's the fat or the kidneys or whatever, or
whether it's a כזית kezayit to eat, that is enough to do
זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. So now the גמרא Gemara continues: רבי יוחנן
דידיה אמר, Rabbi Yochanan didei amar, Rabbi Yochanan in his own name
says: לריח ניחוח, lereiach nichoach, that we learn from the פסוק, pasuk,
it says that you should burn the חלב chelev for a ריח
ניחוח. reiach nichoach. כל שאתה מעלה לריח ניחוח, kol she'ata ma'aleh lereiach
nichoach, that we actually, here's how we learn it from the פסוק.
pasuk. Did I skip a line? No. Okay, here's how we learn
it from the פסוק. pasuk. From the פסוק, pasuk, it's not only
how we learn it from the teaching of רבי יהושוע, Rebbi Yehoshua,
but the פסוק pasuk says you burn the חלב chelev for a
pleasing, a pleasing scent. So anything that's burned, anything that's a pleasing
scent, and therefore obviously it would not be limited to the חלב,
chelev, it would include the lobe and the kidneys. So the גמרא
Gemara
says: כל שהוא לריח ניחוח. kol shehu lereiach nichoach. ואיצטריך למיכתב חלב,
ve'itztarich lemichtav chelev, so why does the Torah have to both give
the specific example of fat, ואיצטריך למיכתב, ve'itztarich lemichtav, לריח ניחוח, lereiach
nichoach, and then it says the more broader phrase of anything that's
a pleasing scent? דאי כתב חלב, de'i ktav chelev, had it said
fat, הוה אמינא חלב אין יותרת ושתי כליות לא, hava amina chelev
in yoteret ushtei klayot lo, I would have said only the fat,
but that if all that's left over is the lobe and the
kidneys, that that would not count and you could not do the
זריקה zrika just for that. כתב רחמנא לריח ניחוח, ktav rachmana lereiach
nichoach, anything that is a pleasing scent. ואי כתב רחמנא לריח ניחוח,
ve'i ktav rachmana lereiach nichoach, had it said that sufficed for sprinkling
the blood, anything that's a pleasing scent. or מנחה mincha *mincha*, maybe
something that's not even part of the body of the animal itself,
maybe even the מנחה mincha. *mincha* that comes with the wine that
comes with the animal. So כתב רחמנא חלב chelev *kasav rachmana chelev*,
fat, to teach you it has to be a part of the
animal itself. So this is the position of Rabbi Yehoshua. Rabbi Yehoshua
says you do not do זריקת הדם zrikat hadam, *zrikas hadam* unless
it is allowing something else at the next stage, either an eating
or a burning. But it has to be an eating or burning
of the animal itself, not of one of the things that come
with the animal.
What is ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach* exactly?
What does
it mean?
No, well, what is a concept that is pleasing to God? Only
parts of the animal make this smell?
I don't know. I mean look, the problem is a lot of
those, a lot of those words are very anthropomorphic, you know, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* translates them in like, you know, in a
very practical halachic sense. The one place where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says that, you know, it means something that's burnt, or it says
ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach* means it has to give off a nice
smell, so you can't pre-char the meat, so that when you put
it on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbeiach* it's not smelling nice. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* never delves into the theology of why, you know, what
does that mean that it's ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*? I mean obviously
those פסוקים *pesukim* are very anthropomorphic, you know.
Yeah, but they were saying certain parts of the animal that's burnt
give a ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*?
No, we're not saying that. No, we're saying ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*
includes anything that's burnt and we would have included anything, not only
meat, we would have included even the מנחה mincha *mincha* that comes
with the animal. And the only reason we exclude the מנחה mincha
*mincha* is the word חלב chelev *chelev* indicates that it has to
be part of the animal itself. So it's quite the opposite. ריח
ניחוח *reiach nichoach* is interpreted very broadly. Only meat, but not because
of the word ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*. No, we're not saying that
that defines ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*. Only the meat suffices that to
allow you to be זורק הדם *zorek hadam*. If you want to
be זורק הדם *zorek hadam*, something of the קרבן korban *korban* has
to be left, and it can't be something that came with the
קרבן korban *korban*, it has to be something of the קרבן korban,
*korban* itself. But that is not a definition of the concept of
ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*. ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach* would have meant anything
that's burnt with the קרבן korban *korban*. ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach* is
a category that includes the מנחת נסכים *minchas nesachim*. But because of
the word חלב *chelev*, that's not telling you what the scope of
ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach* is. חלב *chelev* is telling you what you
need in order to be זורק הדם *zorek hadam*, some part of
the קרבן *korban* itself left over. Okay, but we're not defining the
term חלב *chelev*, ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*.
ריח
ניחוח
*reiach nichoach* is for as far as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s concerned,
ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach* just describes things that are burnt and that
you have to not do it in a way that it won't
smell nice when you burn it, so don't pre-char the meat.
Is there a ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach* that doesn't include meat?
Yes, I mean at least what this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying
is that ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach* is broad enough to include a
מנחת נסכים *minchas nesachim*, a מנחה mincha. *mincha*.
So it's not just meat.
Correct. I actually will point out a point that the נציב *Netziv*
makes, which actually is very relevant for a whole debate about bringing
קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* nowadays, that he says that
because some wanted to argue that you can't bring a קרבן פסח
*Korban Pesach* nowadays because it's not ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*. Because now
that there's no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*, קרבנות korbanot *korbanos*
are not considered to be ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*. So the נציב
*Netziv* points says back that if you look throughout the תורה Torah
*Torah*, every single קרבן *korban* is described as ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*
with the exception of קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*. קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*
does not have to be ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach* because קרבן פסח
*Korban Pesach* is not being brought fundamentally as a sacrifice to God.
קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* is being fundamentally as a way for us
to eat the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*. So therefore the fundamental concept
of ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*, which its primary principle was to be
brought for God, does not apply to the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*.
So we could do it. So according to the נציב *Netziv* we
could bring a קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* nowadays. But whether or not
you translate it into the practical, the sort of conceptual point is
very powerful.
By the monument on Monday?
Yes, exactly. Okay, so let's go on. So what we've seen here
is the famous debate of Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua. Do you
need some remnant of the קרבן *korban* in order to do the
burning by the מנחה Minchah. *mincha* or the זריקה *zrika* of the
דם dam. *dam*? And Rabbi Eliezer says no, if you only can
do that, that's fine, and Rabbi Yehoshua says you need something left
over, and it doesn't have to be the entire, a כזית kezayis
*kezayis* is enough, but you need to be able to do something
of significance afterwards. And it has to be something relating to the
animal itself, the קרבן *korban* itself, not something attendant to the קרבן
*korban*. What is fascinating is the point that Michael said, is that
here a whole discussion is about מנחה Minchah *mincha* and we did
not discuss once how much of the מנחה Minchah *mincha* has to
be left over. All it said was you need something left over.
But elsewhere we know that that is a כזית kezayis *kezayis*. Okay,
let's keep on going.
Now we get to a famous debate that we've sort of seen
before about the significance of what happens after you put the קומץ
kometz *kometz* into the כלי שרת k'li sharet. *klei shares*. שלא בכלי
שרת shelo bekli sharet. פסול pasul. *Shelo b'klei shares pasul*. If you
do the second stage after you took the קומץ kometz *kometz*, you
now put it straight on the fire, and you don't take the
קומץ kometz *kometz* and put it into a כלי שרת k'li sharet.
*klei shares*, which we've been talking about, right? Then it's invalid because
we normally have assumed that putting it into the כלי שרת k'li
sharet *klei shares* is like catching the blood in the כלי שרת
k'li sharet, *klei shares*, it's קבלה *kabala*, and that's the necessary stage
of the עבודה avodah, *avoda*.
Nevertheless, and burning the לבונה levonah *levona* with it.
רבי שמעון Rebi Shimon מכשיר *Rabbi Shimon machshir*. Rabbi Shimon however says
forget it, you don't need a כלי שרת k'li sharet. *klei shares*
at the second stage. Take your קומץ kometz. *kometz*, and the מנחה
Minchah *mincha* has to be in a כלי שרת k'li sharet. *klei
shares*, but take your קומץ kometz *kometz* and then just put it
on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbeiach*. הקטיר hiktir קומצה פעמיים *Hiktir kumtza p'amayim*...
כשר. kasher,
If you burned the קומץ kometz twice, it's כשר, kasher. which does
not mean you let it all burn and you take it off
and then you burn it again. What it means is in two
stages. Okay, you split your קומץ kometz. in half and you burn
it in two stages, that's כשר. kosher So that's a totally different
point. We're going to first focus on this debate that רבי שמעון
Rebi Shimon? presumably does not need a כלי שרת. k'li sharet Well
let's take a look.
Okay, where were we? אמר רבי יהודה בריה דרבי חייא. Amar Rebi
Yehuda breih de-Rebi Chiya.
It's interesting that it's the son of רבי חייא, Rebi Chiya, the
people that really focus
on that's an interesting point. Yeah, they're definitely in different מסכתות, masechtos,
you have different people that focus on them. Okay. אמר רבי יהודה
בריה דרבי חייא, Amar Rebi Yehuda breih de-Rebi Chiya, so רבי יהודה
Rebi Yehuda the son of רבי חייא Rebi Chiya said: מאי טעמא
דרבי שמעון, mai ta'ama de-Rebi Shimon, what's the reason of רבי שמעון?
Rebi Shimon, אמר קרא, Amar kra, because the פסוק pasuk says: קדש
קדשים היא כחטאת וכאשם, Kodesh kodashim hi ka-chatat ve-ka-asham, the מנחה Minchah
is holy of holies like a חטאת chatat and an אשם. asham.
So why is it compared both to a חטאת chatat and an
אשם? asham? To tell you the following. Now, before we say what
it tells you, you have to understand that according to רבי שמעון,
Rebi Shimon he understands that an אשם asham you do not have
to use your right hand. Remember that there's a whole question about
does the תורה Torah have to say כהן kohen and אצבע, etzba,
just כהן, kohen, just אצבע. etzba. Anyway, רבי שמעון Rebi Shimon has
the unusual position that the idea of right hand is specifically by
the application of the blood of the חטאת, chatat, when it says
you put it with your finger on the corners, but by the
blood of the אשם, asham, even if you throw it, you know,
the blood of the אשם asham you don't put with your finger,
you throw from the כלי, kli, זריקת הדם,
and therefore he says you can even use your left hand. So
we start with the idea that רבי שמעון Rebi Shimon acknowledges a
left hand by an אשם. asham. And now רבי שמעון Rebi Shimon
is going to say let me tell you what I'm going to
do with that when it comes to applying it to a מנחה.
mincha Okay, so: בא לעובדה ביד, ba le-ovdah be-yad, so here's what
he says: בא לעובדה ביד, ba le-ovdah be-yad, if you want to
use your hand by the מנחה mincha like you would do with
a חטאת, chatat, עובדה בימין כחטאת, ovdah be-yamin ka-chatat, you'll use your
hand like your right hand like you do with a חטאת. chatat.
בכלי, bi-kli, if you want to use a vessel and you want
to put the קומץ kometz into a vessel, then עובדה בשמאל כאשם,
ovdah be-smol ka-asham, then you can use your left hand like an
אשם. asham. So he says like this: there's no requirement of a
vessel per se after you take the קומץ. kometz Okay, the only
requirement is get this קומץ kometz, on the מזבח. mizbe'ach? What the
תורה tells you is you have two options. This is now like
you have the blood of the קרבן and you're standing right by
the מזבח. mizbe'ach, How would you put it on the מזבח? mizbe'ach
Well, if it's a חטאת, chatat, I dip my finger in and
I put it in like that. Oh, so if you want to
treat this קומץ kometz as if it were a חטאת, chatat, use
your right hand like you would by חטאת chatat and just put
it straight on the מזבח, mizbe'ach you don't need a כלי. kli.
If, however, you have it in a vessel and like you do
by an אשם, asham, you have the blood in a vessel and
you throw it, so you want to go ahead and put this
in a vessel and now from that vessel put it on the
מזבח mizbe'ach and treat it like an אשם, asham, then that's also
good and then you can use your left hand like says רבי
שמעון Rebi Shimon is okay by an אשם. asham. So conceptually, רבי
שמעון Rebi Shimon. is saying is: there's no per se need of
a כלי שרת. k'li sharet There could be two ways of understanding
רבי שמעון. Rebi Shimon One way is there's no need per se
of a כלי שרת k'li sharet, after you take the קומץ. kometz,
There's just a need of putting it on the מזבח mizbe'ach. and
there are two ways you could put it on: using your right
hand or using a כלי. kli. Okay? That's one way of saying
it. The other way of saying it is: there is maybe a
need for a כלי שרת, k'li sharet, but the right hand of
a כהן kohen is considered like a כלי שרת. k'li sharet So
if you use your right hand, you've got it in a כלי
שרת. k'li sharet, If you use your left hand, then make sure
it's in a physical כלי שרת k'li sharet and then it's good.
Two different ways of understanding it, but nevertheless, that's what he says.
You do not need a כלי שרת k'li sharet once you take
the קומץ kometz, if you want to use your right hand.
You said with your left hand you use a vessel?
No, no, that, no. But it's an interesting question. We're going to
see in a minute that because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon downplays a
little bit some aspects of this last stage, that it does make
us a little rethink how that process is considered. We'll see that
in a second.
Okay, that's what רבי יהודה בריה דרבי חייא Rebi Yehuda breih de-Rebi
Chiya said, which is a brilliant דרשה. drasha. Okay, רבי ינאי אמר,
Rebi Yannai amar, רבי ינאי Rebi Yannai says no. He takes this
one step further: כיון שקמצו מכלי שרת, keivan she-kamtzo mi-kli sharet, once
you take the קומץ kometz from the כלי שרת, kli sharet, because
the מנחה mincha is in a כלי שרת, kli sharet מעלהו ומקטירו
אפילו בהמיינו ואפילו במקידה של חרס. ma'alehu u-maktira afilu be-hemyano ve-afilu be-makida
shel cheres. You can go ahead and put it on the מזבח
mizbe'ach, even if you're carrying it in your belt, the כהן's kohen
belt, or even in some type of a pot of pottery. Meaning,
there is no הלכה halacha of כלי שרת kli sharet. and presumably
there's no הלכה halacha even of right hand. What he basically says
is that as opposed to the first opinion, which is like you
need a whole special procedure—you might not need a כלי שרת, kli
sharet, but you need either right or a כלי, kli, or the
way I framed it is your right hand can serve as a
כלי שרת—the kli sharet second approach says once you've taken it and
done the קומץ, kometz that is the primary act of a מנחה.
mincha From this stage on, however you get it on the fire,
I really don't care. Carry it in your belt, carry it in,
you know, your cereal bowl, I don't care what you carry it
in, just get it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach There's no concept at
all of כלי שרת kli sharet or even of a particular defined
process of putting it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach just get it on
the מזבח mizbeach and you're done. Now, you can't say that he
totally devalues that because as we've seen before, everybody agrees for example
that at least there's a פיגול pigul thought that you do, maybe
not when you carry it, but at least when you burn it
on the מזבח mizbeach. there's a פיגול pigul thought. So the act
of putting it on. on the מזבח mizbeach is at least an
act of an עבודה, avoda but it's quite interesting how he is
downplaying the process. And I would suggest the following reason, and this
comes up in a minute in a ברייתא braita we're about to
quote. Because it's actually quite fascinating, you know, normally when the Torah
emphasizes what achieves atonement, it emphasizes the blood. כי הדם הוא על
המזבח יכפר, ki hadam hu al hamizbeach yechapper, כי אני נתתיו לכם
את הדם לכפר על נפשותיכם, ki ani netativ lachem et hadam lachapper
al nafshoteichem, etc. But you have some קרבנות korbanot, that aren't about
blood, like our entire מסכת, masechet, מנחה. Okay, so what achieves the
atonement? And when you think about it, you say, "Wow, the קומץ
kometz is the substitute." But there
are some מנחות minchot that don't even have a קומץ, kometz, which
you burn the whole thing, right? Like a מנחת כהן. minchat kohen.
Now you never have an animal sacrifice where you just say, "Oh,
just put it straight on the מזבח." mizbeach, Even an עולה, olah,
first you do the blood and then you burn it. So the
קומץ, kometz the מנחה inhabits this very unusual space between, if you
would, like the חלב and the דם. dam, On the one hand,
it's burnt as a way of an offering to God, right? That's
sort of like the חלב or the meat of an עולה, olah,
but it also is functioning as a מתיר, mattir, right? It's functioning
like the דם, dam, which isn't something that's burnt up to God,
but it makes it valid. So what I think is being said
here is that maybe this is why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon downplays
the next stage. Because maybe he looks at the next stage more
like the burning of the meat and the fat, and a little
less like the sprinkling of the blood. If you look at it
more like the sprinkling of the blood, you're going to have all
of this emphasis of how you do it, with a כלי שרת,
kli sharet with your right hand, and so on. But you know,
this is burnt. And as something burnt, and you know, where it's
not said the דם, the קומץ kometz, is מכפר. mechapper. It says
like אזכרתה. azkaratah. The קומץ kometz is how the מנחה is remembered,
you know, it's not the same thing as the blood. So maybe
he looks at it a little bit more like the burning of
the fat and the meat and downplays some of the process of
how you get it on the fire. Once being on the fire
is what's more significant than the act of putting it on the
fire.
Okay, so let me understand something, just to make sure. So רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying that
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon, position is consistent elsewhere, and therefore, you know,
you have the right hand or the כלי שרת kli sharet. in
your left hand. Right. And then רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, I think,
also according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon. right?
Yeah, yeah, the long variations of רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon That רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. really doesn't necessarily hold it
through for his position in other קרבנות, korbanot, but here for the
מנחה even more lenient. Exactly.
Okay, there's no parallel to other קרבנות, which is what makes רב
נחמן's Rav Nachman understanding even more interesting.
רבי ינאי's Rabbi Yannai an אמורא. Amora.
Right.
I'm saying not רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, רבי ינאי. Rabbi Yannai. No,
yes, he's an אמורא Amora explaining רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So it
makes it even more interesting because he's really downplaying the act of
burning it on the מזבח mizbeach according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon
רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar, רב נחמן
בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak goes in the other extreme. No,
הכל מודים בקומץ שטעון קידוש. hakol modim bekometz shetaun kiddush.
Everybody, even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that when you take the
קומץ kometz you have to put it in a כלי שרת. kli
sharet. So what is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. saying? That after you've
put it in a כלי שרת, kli sharet the קומץ, kometz, now
you want to get it on the מזבח, mizbe’ach now you can
take it out of the כלי שרת kli sharet with, you know,
your left hand, for example, or you don't have to go straight,
and this was the question that Michael had from the Rambam, you
don't have to go straight from the כלי שרת kli sharet and
turn it over into the fire. You can take it out of
the כלי שרת kli sharet. and burn it from your hand, but
you first have to get it into the כלי שרת. kli sharet.
So we have three explanations of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon, One that
very, you know, makes the debate with him and the חכמים chachamim
smaller. Everybody agrees you take the קומץ kometz and put it in
a כלי שרת. kli sharet. The other question is now, how do
I get it from the כלי שרת kli sharet. on the fire?
Do I upturn the כלי kli or can I now take it
out and put it on the fire as a separate act? But
that seems like more just of a technicality.
It's not what the משנה mishnah says either.
No, it says שלא בכלי שרת. shelo bekli sharet What does it
mean? Does it mean burning it שלא בכלי bikhli שרת or not
using a כלי שרת kli sharet, at all?
It sounds like you're not using one at all.
Okay, so that's the debate. The other position says that no, he
has like two options, you know, you don't need a כלי שרת
kli sharet, but you need your right hand. And then the third,
which is the most extreme and I think the most interesting, says
you don't need your right hand, you don't need a כלי שרת.
kli sharet, After you've taken the קומץ, kometz just get it on
the מזבח mizbe’ach, however you get it on, which is really I
think makes us think about how this is different than blood. Okay,
so let's take a look after Rabbi...
picking up on the second part of the משנה mishnah where it
talks about...
No, no, no, nobody talked about the second part of the משנה.
mishnah. It's interesting, you think that like, you know, maybe a little
bit בדיעבד, bidi'avad, like, you know, putting this into...
It's used as an extreme to point out what his position is.
מיתיבי, Metivei, הקטר חלבים ואיברים ועצים שהעלן. haktar chalavim ve'eivarim ve'etzim shehe'elan.
So we have a ברייתא braita that says the burning and this
is really where I thought that, you know, which was the hint
for רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, that it's much less like blood and
much more like other things that are burnt. Because here's the תוספתא
Tosefta in זבחים. Zevachim. The burning of the fats and the limbs
of an עולה olah and the burning of wood שהעלן, shehe'elan, no
matter how you got them onto the altar, בין ביד בין בכלי,
bein beyad bein bichli, whether you used your hand or a vessel,
בין בימין בין בשמאל, bein biyamin bein bismol, whether you used a
right hand or your left hand, כשרים kesherim are kosher. Okay, that's
not yet our case. Then it says הקומץ, hakometz, the קומץ kometz
of the מנחה והקטורת, vehaktoret, and the incense that's burnt on the
gold altar, שהעלן. shehe'elan. and the לבונה levonah. that's burned שהעלה shehe’elah
that you've put them on the מזבח mizbe’ach בין ביד bein beyad
בין בכלי bein bikhli בין בימין bein beyamin בין בשמאל bein bismol
whether you used your hand or a vessel right or left כשרים
ksherim are kosher. So this is where I think that position gets
its idea from. The idea of these things that are burned is
fundamentally that they're on the מזבח, mizbe’ach not the act of putting
them on, but they're on there and they're burning. And I really
don't care how they got on there. Do I care how the
wood got on there? No, I care that it's on there and
burning. So the same by even by the incense and the קומץ
kometz and the לבונה. levonah. Okay, so question?
Yes. In the ברייתא, brayta, why are they separated? Yeah, I was
going to ask that. תוספות Tosfos asks that.
So
תוספות Tosfos says it might have been because of just oral memory,
oral tradition. You want to teach things in groups of three. Okay,
I would also add that the difference is that the first three
are things that are clearly not sort of being sacrificed. The first
three are the fats and the limbs and the wood, meaning are
not the sacrifice per se. The sacrifice per se, the wood certainly
not, and the fats and the limbs, you would say the blood
is the עיקר. ikar. The last three, these things are the עיקר,
ikar, are the fundamental thing itself: the incense, the קומץ, kometz and
the לבונה. levona, These are the fundamental thing itself, and even these,
it doesn't matter. So it's exactly doing it to make this parallel.
Even these, which you would think are like the act matters, no,
these are about being on the מזבח mizbeach. and burning, not a
particular act of putting them on. Okay, so I think that's a
very powerful תוספתא. tosafta. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Where are we? So the גמרא Gemara says, תיובתא דרבי יהודה בריה
דרבי חייא. tyufta d'Rabbi Yehuda berei d'Rabbi Chiya. This is a contradiction
of רבי יהודה בריה דרבי חייא Rabbi Yehuda berei d'Rabbi Chiya because
it says you can use your left hand and you don't have
to use a vessel, and he says that at least you have
to use your right hand if you're not using a vessel. So
אמר לך amar lecha רבי יהודה בריה דרבי חייא, Rabbi Yehuda berei
d'Rabbi Chiya, he would say back to you, לאצטודים קתני. lastudim ktani.
No, no, it doesn't mean all of these are okay in any
combination. It means if you want to use ביד beyad your hand,
then it would have to be בימין. beyamin. If you want to
use a כלי, kli, בכלי בין בימין bein beyamin בין בשמאל. bein
bismol. So it says you can use your hand or a vessel,
right or left, but it doesn't mean any mix and match. Your
hand or a vessel is true, but if it's your hand it
has to be your right hand, and right or left is true,
but if you're doing right or left it has to be a
vessel. Okay, it doesn't sound like that, but that's what he says.
תא שמע, ta shema, let's look at another ברייתא. brayta. קמצו שלא
מכלי שרת. Kimtzo shelo mikli sharet.
You took the קומץ kometz from the מנחה was not in a
כלי שרת. kli sharet So you took your קומץ kometz, out of
a non-כלי שרת. kli sharet, The מנחה itself was in something that
was not a sanctified vessel. שלא מכלי שרת וקדשו שלא בכלי שרת,
Shelo mikli sharet, vekidsho shelo bikli sharet, or this is 'and' but
it means 'or'. Or you sanctified it in a
non-כלי שרת. kli sharet. והעלהו והקטירו שלא בכלי שרת פסול. Ve'he'elo ve'hiktiro
shelo bikli sharet, pasul. In any of those it's פסול. pasul. You
need to take it from a כלי שרת, kli sharet put it
in a כלי שרת, kli sharet. and then burn it from that
כלי שרת, kli sharet, which would mean the idea of like upturning
the כלי שרת kli sharet, directly onto the fire. Or.
What? Or or and?
It means or. Any of these things were not done correctly, it's
פסול. pasul רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון מכשירים ממתן כלי. Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi
Shimon makhshirim mimatan kli. They say when it comes to putting it
into a כלי שרת, kli sharet that they don't require. Okay, so
that seems very clear against the position that said that they require
it to be put in a כלי שרת. kli sharet, Right? Remember
the last position of רב נחמן Rav Nachman said no, no, all
that he says you don't need is to get it from the
כלי שרת kli sharet, onto the fire. You can take it out
of the כלי שרת. kli sharet. But he said everybody would agree
you have to when you take the קומץ kometz it has to
go into a כלי. kli. Here it says that they don't require
that. Once you took it from a כלי שרת, kli sharet. you
don't have to put it into another כלי. kli. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אימא ממתן כלי. eima mimatan kli. Alright, to rewrite, so
switch the text of the ברייתא. brayta. It doesn't say that they
say it's you don't have to put it in a כלי שרת,
kli sharet, have it say that you don't have to take it
from the כלי שרת kli sharet. onto the fire. Alright, so that's
again a changing of the text. ממתן כלי ואילך. Mimatan kli va'eilach.
From once it was put in the כלי שרת, kli sharet then
you can take it out. Alright, so we are constantly working to
try to prove or disprove the three positions we had. On the
one hand, we had a position that says that according to him,
if you're not using a כלי שרת, kli sharet you need your
right hand. And a ברייתא brayta seemed to say you can use
your left hand. So we said no, no, a left hand only
with a כלי. kli. According to another position, it wanted to say
that he would agree that you have to put it into a
כלי שרת. kli sharet We had a ברייתא brayta says but he
says you don't have to put it into a כלי שרת. kli
shares, So it says, no, no, it means once it's in a
כלי שרת, kli shares then you can do what you want. But
again, the simple sense of all these ברייתות braytas is like the
most extreme read of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon that is once you
take it, you can do whatever you want to get it on
the fire. Okay, so let's take a look. תא
שמע, ta shema, come in here. וחכמים אומרים קומץ טעון כלי שרת.
V'chachamim omrim, kometz taun kli sharet. The rabbis, however, say that the
קומץ kometz requires a כלי שרת. kli shares. כיצד קמצו מכלי שרת
וקדשו בכלי שרת והעלהו והקטירו בכלי שרת. Keitzad? Kimtzo mikli sharet, u'kidesho
bikli sharet, ve'he'elo ve'hiktiro bikli sharet. You take the קומץ kometz from
a
כלי שרת kli shares, and you put it into a כלי שרת
kli shares when you after you took the
קומץ kometz, and you go up to the מזבח mizbeach and then
you upturn the כלי שרת kli shares. and you get it on
the fire.
רבי שמעון אומר כיון שקמץ. Rabbi Shimon omer, keivan she'kamat. Once you
took it from a כלי שרת, kli shares, you can put it
on the fire without a כלי שרת kli shares, and that's enough.
You have to take the original taking of the קומץ, kometz you
don't have to worry about any כלים. keilim. So again that proves
that after the original taking, you don't need to put it into
a כלי שרת. kli shares. So אימא eima switch the text, כיון
שקמצו וקדשו בכלי שרת, keivan shekamzo v'kidsho b'kli shares, once you took
the קומץ kometz and put it in a כלי שרת, k'li sharet?
then מעלה ומקטירו ודיו, maaleh umaktiro v'dayo, then you can get on
the fire. So we keep on switching the text, but again all
the evidence is that once you take the קומץ kometz for Rabbi
Shimon, it does not matter how that קומץ komatz gets on the
fire.
Okay,
תא שמע, ta shma, come in here.
All of the evidence so far is like the middle position, Rav
Yannai, which I think is the most interesting position, which really says
this is not like blood. There's no, once you took the קומץ,
komatz we don't really focus on the process, we just focus on
the fact that you got it on the fire. Okay, תא שמע,
ta shma, come in here. קומץ בימינו ונתן בשמאלו, kometz b'yamino v'natan
b'smalo, you took the קומץ komatz, in your right hand and then
you switched it to your left hand, okay, יחזיר לימינו, yachzir l'yamino,
put it back into your right hand and now bring it. בשמאלו
וחישב, bishmalo v'chishav, if while it was in your left hand you
had a thought of פיגול, pigul,
וחישב עליו, v'chishav alav, בין חוץ למקומו בין חוץ לזמנו, bein chutz
limkomo bein chutz lizmano, whether you had a thought about חוץ למקומו
chutz limkomo or חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, פסול ואין בו כרת, pasul
v'ein bo kares, it's פסול pasul but there's no כרת, kares, because
in your left hand is not in a position where you could
be מקריב makriv it on the מזבח. mizbeach. We're going to skip
the next three lines, it's a whole debate of whether they should
be there or not and it's very confusing if they're there, so
we're just going to skip to like three lines directly under the
little ב beis in brackets or two lines directly under, דברי רבי
אליעזר ורבי שמעון. divrei Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon. Those are the words
of Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Shimon, וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, and the
sages say, now at the beginning of line number five, וחכמים אומרים,
vachachamim omrim, the sages say, כיון שנתנו לשמאלו פסלתו מתנתו. keivan shenatno
lishmalo psalto matnato.
Once you put it in your left hand, you've invalidated it. Okay,
so this seems to be the straight debate. The חכמים chachamim say
the left invalidates, so you put it in your left hand, you
can't return it back to your right. Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Shimon
say no, no, the left doesn't invalidate, it's not good enough so
you can't, if you have a thought of פיגול, pigul, it's not
meaningful, but,
one minute, but you can put it back in your right. Now,
what is this middle stage, that the left is not enough for
your פיגול pigul thoughts to be meaningful, but it's not enough of
a problem that you can put it back in your right? That
works best with the explanation that you have a choice. I can
either do it in my right without a כלי שרת k'li sharet.
or in my left and I need a כלי kli שרת. So
if, right, remember that position, so if it's in my left, I
don't have a כלי kli שרת, so it's not yet, it's not
meaningful and my thought of פיגול pigul isn't meaningful because I don't
have a כלי kli שרת, I just have it in my hand.
On the other hand, it's not invalid in my left, there's not
an idea that left is an invalidity because we acknowledge that there
are ways that the left can work. So therefore, either essentially if
it's in my left, either get it into a כלי kli. or
get it back into my right hand, but since the left by
itself without a כלי kli, doesn't work, therefore my thought of פיגול
pigul is not meaningful. Okay, the simple explanation of this ברייתא braisa
works with that position that according to Rabbi Eliezer, you have a
choice of left with a כלי kli. or right without a כלי.
k'li. When it's in your left without a כלי, k'li. it's not
valid right now, but because left is not totally off base, it's
not פסול pasul either, and therefore you can return it to your
right hand.
I'm sorry, I'm a little confused as to, when he says חוץ
לזמנו chutz lizmano or חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, it's פסול ואין בו
כרת, pasul v'ein bo kares, but you know,
פסול pasul is דרבנן derabbanan not דאורייתא. deoraisa. I mean, that's basically
the way to understand, not for any intrinsic reason, it's basically not
a problem in your left hand. That's the way רש״י Rashi indicates.
Okay, but wait, then why is it פסול pasul at all?
דרבנן, derabbanan, sometimes we פסול pasul, things, that's what the discussion about
a number of areas where it really shouldn't have been פסול, pasul
but we said פסול pasul, anyway.
Okay, so I'm sorry, so we're saying that your thoughts matter enough
to make it פסול, pasul, but
דרבנן.
derabbanan. מאיקר הדין, meikar hadin, your thoughts don't matter when it's in
your left
hand, okay?
They don't, so they don't want to say it's דאורייתא deoraisa because
then it doesn't work.
Okay, so now let's see how the גמרא Gemara analyzes this.
מאי טעמא, mai taama, what's the reasoning that according to the רבנן
rabbanan that the left hand
invalidates? משום דבעי קדושה בכלי, mishum d'baei kedusha b'kli, because the rabbis
hold very simply that when you take the קומץ komatz out, you
have to right now put it in a vessel, it needs קדושת
כלי, kedushas kli, no question.
וכיון שנתנו לשמאלו, v'keivan shenatno lishmalo, instead of putting it in a
vessel you put it in your left hand, נעשה כדם שנשפך מצואר
בהמה על הרצפה, naaseh k'dam she-nishpach mitzvar behemah al haritzpah,
it's like the blood, meaning they understand that the putting it in
the vessel is like the catching of the blood with a כלי
k'li שרת. If the, it needs immediately to go into the כלי.
k'li. If it goes somewhere else, that invalidated it. So if blood
comes out of the animal's neck on the ground, you can't now
put it in the vessel, it has to be caught from the
neck of the animal. If your taking up of the קומץ komatz
goes into your hand rather than a vessel, that invalidated it. It's
like the blood spilled on the ground.
ואספו, v'asfo, and even if you gathered it afterwards, שפסול, shepasul, it's
פסול, that's why they say your left hand you cannot fix. So
that's the רבנן. rabbanan. Let's understand Rabbi Eliezer. מכלל דרבי אליעזר ורבי
שמעון לא בעו מתן כלי, michlal d'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon lo bau
matan kli, but why does Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Shimon allow you
to go from your left and back to your right? So once
again you see that according to them, you don't need to go
straight into a כלי. k'li, It's not like רב נחמן Rav Nachman
tried to say, oh, they would also agree you have to go
into a כלי. k'li, No, they say you can take it with
your right and put it into your left. You don't have to
first use the כלי k'li. stage. So the גמרא Gemara says תיופתא
דרב נחמן תיופתא. tyufta d'Rav Nachman tyufta. That is a complete contradiction
of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, which is a good thing because all
the other evidence had contradicted it anyway. Now the גמרא Gemara finally
admits it, okay? So רב נחמן Rav Nachman said that even רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. agree that after you
take the קומץ komatz you have to put it in a כלי.
k'li, All the evidence shows no, once you take the קומץ komatz,
get it on the מזבח mizbeach. anyway, and here we've admitted that
that's true because if they really said you need a כלי, k'li
putting in your left hand would invalidate. Now, what else can we
infer from this ברייתא? braita? So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
לרבי יהודה בריה דרבי חייא מסייעא ליה. l'Rabbi Yehuda brei d'Rabbi Chiyya
mesaye'a lei.
According to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the son of רבי חייא, Rabbi
Chiyya, it's a support for the reason I said because it sounds
like left is somewhat problematic, right? You have to get it back
to your right. So that works best with that first position, that
you have two options: left with a כלי, k'li right without a
כלי. k'li. So left...
Wait, wasn't that the middle one?
What? No, that was the first one. Left is therefore, that's why
the ברייתא braita says return it to your right because in your
left without a כלי, it's neither. And therefore, it might not invalidate,
but at least it has to be corrected. That works out very
well. But the גמרא Gemara. says לרבי ינאי לימא תיהוי תיופתא. l'Rabbi
Yannai leima tehei tyufta.
According to רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, which is the one right that
that I'm attracted to, that says the most, you know, the most
stark, which says once you take the קומץ, komatz, I don't care
what you do to get it on the מזבח. mizbeach Left, right,
foot, hand, whatever you want to do. He didn't say foot, but
okay. Hit it on your belt, get it on the מזבח. mizbeach.
So why is left a problem according to him? So how does
he explain this? לימא תיהוי תיופתא? leima tehei tyufta? Maybe it'll be
a contradiction? אמר לך רבי ינאי. amar lach Rabbi Yannai. רבי ינאי
Rabbi Yannai would say, אנא דאמרי כהאי תנא דהכשר ולאו כהאי תנא.
ana d'amri kehai tanna d'hechsher v'lav kehai tanna. No, I had that
whole תוספתא Tosefta that supported me. You're right. This ברייתא braita doesn't
go like me. This ברייתא braita thinks left hand is a little
bit of a problem for רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon But I had
the whole ברייתא braita that said that you can do your right,
your left, yes a vessel, not a vessel, do whatever however you
want. And I don't think it means like only some of those
cases work. I think it means like its simple sense and therefore
I have plenty of תנאי Tannaic support. So this doesn't work with
me, but the other ברייתא braita did. So what you have now
is this great debate, I think, within רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, who
says, and now we find out it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
רבי שמעון, that you don't need a כלי after you take the
קומץ komatz to the point that maybe on the one hand it's
like you don't need a כלי but you need a substitute כלי.
You need your right hand. Then it's not such a big conceptual
debate. But the other position says no, after you take the קומץ
komatz. get it on the מזבח mizbe'ach, anyway you want. And as
I said, that really is, and that ברייתא braita that compared it
to the burning of the fat and the meat and the wood,
points out that the קומץ kometz, is not exactly the same as
the blood. And that in some ways maybe the act of putting
it is not as significant.
Does רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai say it must come from a כלי
שרת?
No. He says take the קומץ, kometz oh yeah, the original מנחה
has to be in a כלי שרת. But once you've taken your
קומץ, kometz, from that point on just get it on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach Okay, so let's take a look. הקטיר קומצה פעמיים כשרה. hiktir
komtza pa'amayim k'sheira. Now we go on to say that if you
did it in two halves it's כשרה. k'sheira. You broke your קומץ
kometz in two halves and you did it and you did it
in halves, it's כשרה. k'sheira. So אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי. amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. So רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi says פעמיים ולא פעמי פעמיים. pa'amayim v'lo pa'amei pa'amayim. In two
halves, but not in halves of halves.
How does that make a difference? What? When it's not all together...
Well the גמרא Gemara is going to tell you why it's going
to make a difference, okay? In two halves but not in halves.
Not... not in quarters. ורבי יוחנן אמר פעמיים ואפילו פעמי פעמיים. v'Rabbi
Yochanan amar pa'amayim v'afilu pa'amei pa'amayim.
You can even burn it up in quarters. מאי בינייהו? mai beinayhu?
Why...
what's the source of their debate? אמר רבי זירא יש קומץ פחות
משני זיתים ויש הקטרה פחות מכזית איכא בינייהו. amar Rabbi Zeira yesh
komatz pachos mishnei zeisim v'yesh haktara pachos m'kezayis ika beinayhu.
So although we have said before, right, in the earlier משנה, Mishna,
that in order to bring up, you know, that you need that
כזית kezayis. is a significant amount, כזית kezayis. is a significant amount
for שיריים. shirayim.
It's also a significant amount for הקטרה. haktara. For example, if somebody
is מקטיר maktir outside of the בית המקדש, you need to be
מקטיר maktir a כזית. kezayis, You need to burn a כזית. kezayis,
So the question is, nevertheless, we're going to revisit this question. Is
it considered, here it's not that of all I'm doing is a
כזית, kezayis, I'm doing it in stages. Remember the גמרא Gemara before
that talked about doing a sesame seed's worth at a time? So
I'm doing it at stages. I do less than a כזית, kezayis,
less than a כזית, kezayis? less than a כזית, kezayis? and in
the end I burn the קומץ. kometz Is that considered significant if
at each stage it was less than a כזית? kezayis. So that's
at the source of their debate. So let's see how the גמרא
Gemara spells it out. So the first two parts of the question
is, does... are there people whose hand's breadth is less than two
כזיתים kezaysim and is it considered to do a הקטרה haktara when
it's less than a כזית? kezayis. איכא בינייהו. ika beinayhu. רבי יהושע
בן לוי סבר, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi savar, רבי יהושע בן לוי
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi holds, אין קומץ פחות משני זיתים, ein komatz
pachos mishnei zeisim,
that any person's hand's breadth is always minimally two זיתים. zeisim. So
therefore when the משנה Mishna says you can do it in halves,
each half is going to be at least how big? If every
hand's breadth is at least two זיתים, zeisim, each half is at
least a
זית. zayit. ואין הקטרה פחותה מ- v'ein haktara p'chusa mi- כזית. kezayis.
So there's no idea of doing a הקטרה, haktara, it's not considered
an act less than a כזית. kezayis The משנה mishnah does not
implicitly allow for that. So I'm not going to let you do
it into quarters, which means that each part of the process will
be less than a כזית. kezayis רב יוחנן סבר, Rav Yochanan savar,
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan holds יש קומץ פחות משני זיתים, yesh kometz
pachot mishenei zeisim,
some people's hands breaths are less than two זיתים, zeisim, and if
the משנה mishnah says you can do it in halves, that means
what is the משנה mishnah telling you? שיש הקטרה פחותה מכזית, sheyesh
haktara pichusa mikezayis, the משנה mishnah is telling you that even if
each act is less than a כזית kezayis it counts, and therefore
once you can do less than a כזית kezayis who cares if
you're doing it in halves or you're doing it in quarters. Okay,
so there's not really a principal debate of halves versus quarters, the
principal debate is if you're doing a process where each act is
less than a כזית kezayis but it's all part of a process
that's a full קומץ, kometz is that going to be enough or
not? I should point out by the way with all of the
funny debates about how big a כזית kezayis is, if you think
about how big a normal person's קומץ kometz is and that we're
assuming that on the average this is at least the size of
two כזיתים, kezaysim, that's certainly something to think about when it comes
to eating a כזית kezayis? of מצה. matzah.
Okay, ask for that, how do you get from there to like
three quarters of a מצה?
matzah? Okay, so actually נתן סליפקין Natan Slifkin has a great article
which I will link you to which talks about how the כזית
kezayis grew in you know in size in terms of הלכה. halacha.
And one of the things that he points out is that you
know all of the ספרדי ראשונים Sephardi Rishonim just say how big
is a כזית? kezayis? Size of an olive. All the אשכנזים Ashkenazim
do all of these חשבונות cheshbonos and come up with bigger sizes.
And he says he brings he shows all of this evidence that
there were no olives in France and Germany and they had never
seen an olive. Oh. And they even say it. They even say
since we don't know how big an olive is you have to
be careful. And then the ראש Rosh says oh now I've seen
now that I've been in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael I've seen olives
and so part of the whole growth of the size of the
כזית kezayis had to do with their not ever having seen an
olive.
You're saying it's all based on lack of knowledge?
Well, basically. Anyway, I'll send you the article. Okay, but here...
so this is the first inflated כזית?
Yeah, but I'll send you the article, he he tracks the whole...
meaning would you say now that like we know what an olive
is we could go back...
some people say that,
some people say that.
Yes, you can look at the article. Anyway, okay, so that's the
debate. So but again what we get from today's דף היומי Daf
Yomi is a קומץ, kometz this amount between my three fingers, is
probably is right around the size of two כזיתים. kezaysim.
Anyway, so that's the גמרא Gemara and therefore the debate is is
that can you do each part of the process less than a
כזית if in the sum it's going to be a קומץ worth.
Let's go on now in the גמרא. Gemara איתמר, Itmar, it was
said: קומץ מאימתי מתיר שיריים באכילה. Kometz mei'emaisai matir shirayim ba'achilah. And
this I think very much ties into what we just discussed on
the עמוד א'. amud aleph. When does the קומץ consider valid? And
again this shows how it's not like the blood. When does the
blood mean you can eat the meat? As soon as it hits
the wall. But when I put the קומץ on the fire it
hasn't yet the smoke hasn't risen up, it hasn't yet been considered
you know offered, burnt, until... so at what stage is it offered?
And this again points to the idea of
downplaying the act of placing because it's not just the placing, what
makes it valid is that then it catches fire and it burns
which happens by itself.
So what's the question?
So the question is at what stage has it become valid? At
what stage can I now eat the rest of...
like the moment it starts getting burnt?
But that's not what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Why
not? It's different than blood. It's not just the placing, it's about
being being מעלה לריח ניחוח. ma'aleh lerei'ach nicho'ach. So let's take a
look.
קומץ מאימתי מתיר שיריים באכילה. Kometz mei'emaisai matir shirayim ba'achilah. When does
it make the remnant permissible to be eaten? רבי חנינא אומר משימשלה
בו האור. Rabbi Chanina omer mishetimshila bo ha'or. So רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina says what Michael says, as soon as the fire takes hold
of it. רבי יוחנן אומר, Rabbi Yochanan omer, no,
משיצית בו האור ברובו. mishetatzis bo ha'or berubo. You need most of
it to have been taken over by the fire. And רש"י Rashi
emphasizes the difference of ברובו berubo versus the other phrase doesn't have
ברובו. berubo. He does not emphasize the difference of the verbs of
תמשלה timshila versus תצית. tatzis. I don't know if others do. But
he says the question is when it starts burning or the majority.
אמר ליה רב יהודה לרבה בר רב יצחק, Amar lei Rav Yehuda
leRabba bar Rav Yitzchak, אסברא לך טעמא דרבי יוחנן. asbera lach ta'ama
deRabbi Yochanan. Let me explain to you the reason of רב יוחנן
Rav Yochanan that needs the majority to be burning. אמר קרא, Amar
kra, the פסוק pasuk says: והנה עלה קיטור הארץ כקיטור הכבשן, Vehineh
ala kitor ha'aretz kekitor hachivshan, and the the pillar of smoke from
the earth rose up like the pillar of smoke from an oven.
This is with the destruction of סדום ועמורה. Sodom veAmorah. So he
says
אין כבשן מעלה קיטור, ein kivshan ma'aleh kitor, an oven does not
raise up a pillar of smoke עד שתצית האור ברובו, ad shetatzis
ha'or berubo, until the fire seizes the majority of the food inside
of it. So what has to do is that this is a
הקטרה, haktara, you are מקטיר, maktir, which is קיטור. kitor. The verb
of להקטיר lehaktir means to offer up as incense, doesn't mean to
put on a fire, right? When I say I'm going to cook,
it doesn't mean I put on a fire. This is also לערב
שבת le'erev shabbos question, right? The act of cooking doesn't take place
the second it's on the fire. It requires that the thing continue
to cook. So the act of being מקטיר, maktir, you know, in
English we don't even have a verb The verb for it which
says burning incense right but the act of if you would incensing
okay that's a different context but anyways the act of הקטיר means
to cause the pillar of smoke to rise. That doesn't happen the
second you put it on; that happens after the fire seizes hold
of it. What?
To smoke something? To smoke.
But that more or less means like if you smoke lox that
the smoke gets absorbed into the thing. This is to make the
thing rise up with smoke.
Who says our standard needs to be קיטור כשום kittur keshum though?
No, it's just from there we learn that להקטיר lehaktir means that
the majority of the thing...
I would say just the opposite. I'd say in that case since
it's comparing to קיטור כשום kittur keshum that's like a higher, you
know, it's like something else. Otherwise קיטור kittur would be even less.
I say it would be, it's you know, it's the best proof.
Okay, got it. אמר ליה—so Amar leh that's what he says. So
he says,
אמר ליה רבין בר רב אדא לרבא, Amar leh Ravin bar Rav
Ada le-Rava, אמי תלמידך ami talmidecha your students say, אמר רב עמרם
amar Rav Amram in the name of רב עמרם, Rav Amram, תניא
אין לי אלא דברים שדרכן ליקרב בלילה, tanya ein li ela dvarim
she-darkan le-hikarev ba-layla, that רב עמרם Rav Amram would quote this ברייתא,
braita, that I only know things that are normally burnt at night.
What are things that are normally burnt at night? כגון איברים ופדרים
שהעלון ומקטירן מבא השמש, kegon evarim u-fadarim she-ha'alu u-maktiran mi-bo ha-shemesh, like
the fats and the limbs of an עולה olah that are put
on the fire after the sunset ומתאכלין והולכין כל הלילה u-mit-achlin ve-holchin
kol ha-layla and they can be consumed and you keep them on
the fire the whole night, that we know that you burn the
fats throughout the whole
night כולה. kulah. דברים שדרכן ליקרב ביום, dvarim she-darkan le-hikarev ba-yom, but
things that are normally burnt during the
day, כגון הקומץ והלבונה והקטורת, kegon ha-kometz ve-ha-levona ve-ha-ktoret, so here are
all the things that we normally don't consider to be like fat.
We consider to be like the קרבן itself, the קומץ and the
לבונה, right the frankincense, והקטורת, ve-ha-ktoret, the incense that's burnt on the
gold מזבח, mizbe'ach ומנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח, u-minchat kohanim u-minchat kohen
mashiach, the מנחת כהנים minchat kohanim which is fully burnt, ומנחת נסכים
u-minchat nesachim and the מנחה of the of the wine that comes
with the with the קרבן, שהעלון ומקטירן מבא השמש. she-ha'alu u-maktiran mi-bo
ha-shemesh.
So how do I know that those too I can bring after
sunset? So the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, a minute ago
you said these are things that have to be brought during the
day. Now you want to know how do I know I can
burn these things after sunset?
No, no, והא אמרת
דרכן ליקרב ביום. ve-ha amarta darkan le-hikarev ba-yom. Wait a minute, the
גמרא says, this ברייתא braita says how do I know things that
are normally brought during the day like the קומץ I can bring
after sunset? Didn't you just say they have to be brought during
the day? אלא אם בא השמש, ela im ba ha-shemesh, how do
I know that I can bring them right before sunset? שמתאכלין והולכין
כל הלילה she-mit-achlin ve-holchin kol ha-layla
and they can nevertheless continue to burn throughout the night, מנין, minayin,
how do I know this? תלמוד לומר זאת תורת העולה. talmud lomar
zot torat ha-olah.
This is the law of the עולה, olah, ריבה, riba, that's coming
to include. So the פשט pshat of this is that we learn
out from this that you put the קטורת ktoret on the fire
right before sunset and it continues to burn after sunset. So doesn't
that show that you need that it's considered a valid הקטרה haktara
as soon as it gets on the fire? Because for it to
be valid it has to take place before sunset and here it
says it continues to burn after sunset. So the גמרא says והאי
אם בא השמש ve-hai im ba ha-shemesh if you put it on
the fire right at sunset לא משכחת לה דתצית האור ברובו, la
mishkachas la she-tatzi ha-or be-rubo, the fire doesn't have a chance to
seize the majority of it before sunset. So the גמרא says no,
לא קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult, כאן לקלוט כאן להקטיר. kan
liklot kan lehaktir. There's a difference between it being staying on the
מזבח and about putting it on. What does that mean? That yes,
you're right that once you put it on the מזבח it does
not, you don't take—if you put it on before sunset you do
not have to take it off even if it finishes burning after
sunset. But for it to really become valid it does have to
finish burning and that can—at—it does have to burn the majority of
it has to be seized by fire and that can happen after
sunset. So what the גמרא is saying is a fascinating thing and
I want you to think for a minute about how we would
say about this by שבת, Shabbos, right? What the גמרא is saying
is like this, I will say this does not count as a
putting of the קטורת ktoret on to make the קרבן כשר until
the fire seized most of it. But
the עבודה avoda has to be done before sunset, that you all
you have to do is put it on the fire before sunset.
The finishing of the process of most of it's being seized by
the fire for it to be considered valid that can happen after
sunset. Now you could say that's bizarre if that's what makes this
valid shouldn't it all have to be before sunset? But this exactly
points to the difference between an act that is done by a
human and then finishes by itself. And I would ask you this
question about שבת, Shabbos, if I put something in an oven one
minute before the end of the day or שבת Shabbos or, you
know, there's צאת הכוכבים tzeit ha-kochavim here but whatever it is but
it doesn't really finish cooking till after צאת tzeit have I violated
שבת Shabbos or not? Is it the putting on is my act
of cooking with the condition that eventually it finishes or is it
no the actual whole process has to be? Now some say that
by some things we know that even if the process finishes after
שבת Shabbos like planting seeds I'm only חייב chayav once they take
root they only take root two weeks later. Afterwards. Okay, but if
I planted it on שבת Shabbos and it took root two weeks
afterwards, I'm חייב. chayiv. It doesn't all have to happen during שבת,
Shabbos, but with every different מלאכה, melacha, there's a question of how
do you define the act. So here what he is saying is
the act of the עבודה is putting it on the fire, and
only that has to be done before sunset, but it only becomes
valid once the fire spreads. And I think this provides a very
nice parallel to the position of Rabbi Shimon, who we said before
doesn't care how you got it on the fire, he focuses on
the fact that it actually burns. That here actually,
some of the process is not being done by you anyway, it
just continues naturally, and that then raises the question about how much
of this is really a formal process that needs to be done
by you. Okay, we will end here.